Narrator: 1
Steve: Mum and Dad came from very different families.
Dad’s father was a garage mechanic, and his mother was a waitress.
They were Welsh Catholics, very traditional.
Mum’s parents, on the other hand, were, er, very well-educated.
Her father was Burmese, he was an expert in Burmese music,
and her mother was half Burmese and half English,
and she’d been very active politically in the independence movement in Burma.
So, with these two very different sets of parents,
my mum and dad were quite different people, and I think they still are.
Bridget: So, my parents are both doctors.
In fact, the family mythology is that they met
because they were both dissecting the same dead body.
Mum had come to London in her early teens.
She’d left Burma during the war and spent, er,
several years in India before coming to the UK with her mother and her two sisters.
Narrator: 2
Steve: I was actually a bit embarrassed about Mum’s culture,
because it was so different from everybody else at school.
So, the idea of having this, kind of, Burmese family –
not that anybody really at school knew where Burma was –
um, it was quite different.
Bridget: I wasn’t so much aware of Mum and Dad coming from different cultures
as I was aware of the fact that Mum wasn’t white,
and so she didn’t fit in, and, in that regard, neither did we.
I think, in terms of culture, what I was more conscious of was,
um, the fact that they came from very different educational and class backgrounds.
So, my mum was really interested in literature, she loved music,
and she used to listen to the cricket, and she wasn’t a Catholic.
My dad didn’t have much time for literature, or music, or cricket.
He was interested in rugby, pot boilers, and spy stories, and history.
Narrator: 3
Steve: As a child, I felt there were not many positive things
about growing up in a multicultural family.
We grew up in the 1970s, and it was a time when, I think,
racism was not challenged in schools,
and so we were quite often the victims of bullying because of the fact that we looked different,
because our mum was from Burma and physically
we all take after our mum much more than our dad.
Bridget: I wouldn’t really say – I wouldn’t really describe our family as a multicultural family,
largely because there was no Burmese spoken.
My mother had forgotten her Burmese when she went to India.
I would rather describe our family as a mixed-race family.
And, to be frank, that was quite tough.
It was quite tough being in the 1970s, growing up in south Wales,
which was a very white region of the country, um, and, you know,
quite frankly, enduring a lot of, um, very explicit racism.
So, that was quite a big downside.
The upside, I think…well, the food.
Um, but also, I think, that we grew up appreciative of other points of view.
I think that we are all, in our different ways,
sensitive to when people don’t fit in and want to, kind of,
help people through that and, um, yeah, and I actually think that that is a social benefit.
Narrator: 4
Steve: In spite of feeling very different when we were at school,
our upbringing was, I think, very typical middle-class British family.
Um, we watched television programmes,
did the sorts of things that white middle-class British people do.
Um, so there wasn’t much about the daily life
that was very different from what other kids at school were doing.
Bridget: I think that, um, my sense of identity as a child
was very much shaped by the fact that we were brought up in south Wales.
So, there was very definitely an identity of, um,
Welshness among our peers, as opposed to Englishness.
And there is no question that Welshness at that time
was really associated with being born in Wales and also, crudely, being white.
So, we didn’t really have the option of being Welsh, um, or of being English,
and I didn’t feel Burmese because of not speaking Burmese.
So, I remember talking to my grandmother about it, and –
and whether she felt British or English – and she said, ‘I just feel me.’
And, I guess, that’s the same as I’ve felt and feel. I just feel ‘me’.
Narrator: 5
Steve: Of course, where there was a difference with the other kids at school
was in the food that we ate,
because Mum loved to cook and she would make all sorts of interesting dishes with spices.
And, of course, even though it was all delicious,
again we felt a little bit embarrassed going to school the next day
if our clothes smelled of spices, or if our breath smelled of garlic.
And when we took friends home from school,
I was quite keen for Mum to make fish fingers and chips,
and not delicious homemade curry because I didn’t want people, kind of,
making fun of me because we were eating funny food.
Bridget: I think one aspect of my life that was different was
that I was really surrounded in the family by very high-achieving women.
Which isn’t to say that I felt pressure from that, um,
it was just normal for women to go to work as professionals and – and to be a mum.
And, I just took that for granted and now, looking back, I realize that,
actually, that was quite unusual.
Narrator: 6
Steve: I think that my English and Burmese, er,
heritage has influenced what I do today, very much.
My restaurant, Ma Khin Café, er, has Burmese food, um, very real Burmese food, um,
lots of dishes that you would actually eat if you went to Burma today,
and also, er, food from the countries that are around Burma,
and that have influenced Burmese cuisine, because, like all cuisines,
Burma’s food culture has developed through the influence of the countries that surround it,
the people that have travelled to live there, the people that have invaded it,
the people that have occupied it.
Bridget: Being half Burmese and half British –  I wouldn’t say English –
um, has definitely influenced what I do today.
In fact, I think, really, in some ways you could say I’ve built my whole life around it.
So, I’m now an academic at the University of Bristol and I’m a professor of migration and citizenship,
so my research is all around questions of migration, race, and belonging,
so you could say it’s my life work.
And, of course, it’s deeply influenced the book that I’ve put together with my brother, Steve.
Nobody else could have written that book, that book came from, yeah,
growing up as mixed-race children in south Wales.
In that respect it’s as much about our history as it is about our grandmother and Burmese history.